Guide to the St. Joseph African Methodist Episcopal Church fan collection, 1940s RL.11880
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
St. Joseph African Methodist Episcopal Church fan collection
1940s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
St. Joseph's African Methodist Episcopal Church (Durham, N.C.)
RL.11880
1.0 Linear Feet
St. Joseph African Methodist Episcopal Church was founded in Durham, N.C. in 1869. The church fan collection consists of 16 fans distributed to congregation members. Fans depict on one side devotional and pastoral scenes; on the other side are religious and promotional messages from various Durham, N.C. African American-owned businesses. Businesses represented include automotive repair shops, bakeries, flower shops, funeral parlors, grocery stores and laundry services. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Biographical / Historical
St. Joseph African Methodist Episcopal Church was founded in Durham, N.C. in 1869. The Rev. Edian Markum (Markham) founded the Union Bethel AME Church in Durham in 1869. In 1892 it moved to a new building at 804 Fayetteville Street and was renamed St. Joseph African Methodist Episcopal Church under the guidance of Rev. Andrew Chambers. In 1976 the church relocated to 2521 Fayetteville; the 804 Fayetteville St. location became the Hayti Heritage Center, focused on African American culture and history. (source: https://www.stjosephame.org/history; https://www.guidestar.org/profile/56-1152267)
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The St. Joseph African Methodist Episcopal Church fan collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2000.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following collections:
Alvin T. Parnell photographs of Durham, N.C.
Durham Chamber of Commerce records
Durham County (N.C.) papers
Collection Overview
The church fan collection consists of 16 fans distributed to congregation members. Fans depict on one side devotional and pastoral scenes; on the other side are religious and promotional messages from various Durham, N.C. African American-owned businesses. Businesses represented include automotive repair shops, bakeries, flower shops, funeral parlors, grocery stores and laundry services.
African American business enterprises -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; African American churches; African American churches -- North Carolina; African Americans -- Durham (N.C.); African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History; Advertising; African Americans -- Religion; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
- 1. African American children praying, 1940s (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Back side: Hayti Shoe Repair Shop, Selective Service, S.W. Shaw prop., phone R-4601, 713 Fayetteville St. Durham N.C.
  Biographical / Historical
  713 Fayetteville was part of a commercial building constructed around 1930. It was originally home to Max Zuckerman meat market; then College View Shoe Repair, later renamed Hayti Shoe Repair (around 1941); H&H Sport Shop (1957); Palms Beauty Salon (1959); Modern Beauty Salon (1968). The building was demolished around 1972. (http://www.opendurham.org/buildings/713-717-fayetteville)
- 2. African American girl and woman watering flowers, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Scarborough & Hargett Funeral Directors, Ambulance Service, phone J-3721, "Faithful, Efficient and Continuous Service Since 1888," Durham N.C. Photograph of children captioned "Playtime at Scarborough Nursery School."
  Scarborough & Hargett was founded by J.C. Hargett in Kinston and joined by John Clarence Scarborough in 1888. The firm relocated to Durham in 1905. In 1906 Scarborough became the first African American in North Carolina to receive an embalmers license. In 1925 Scarborough founded the Scarborough Nursery Home and School, the first licensed nursery school in the state. The firm continues as the Scarborough & Hargett Celebration of Life Center in Durham. (https://www.scarboroughhargettcelebration.com/who-we-are/history-and-staff)
- 3. African American woman with basket of peaches, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Farrington's Grocery Market, Novey Farrington prop., "Fresh Home-Killed Meats Fancy Groceries of All Kinds Prices Within Reach," phone J-1635, 2409 Fayetteville St. Durham N.C.
- 4. African American woman with dog, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Bull City Barber and Beauty Shop, G.P. Holloway prop., R.L. Chavis mgr., "It Pays to Look Your Best--You Will Like Our Quick and Courteous Service," 410 East Pettigrew Street Durham N.C., phone L-0912.
  410 Pettigrew was part of a commercial building constructed in 1928 by Holloway who established the barber shop in the 410 bay where it remained until the building was demolished in 1977. Holloway also co-founded a barber college in the 1940s, at one time the only licensed barber college for African Americans in North Carolina. (http://www.opendurham.org/buildings/412-east-pettigrew)
- 5. Gayle Arnetta Ray, "Call Grand Daddy for Service", 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: J.H. Ray, Sr., J.H. Ray Jr., Douglas C. Ray, Harold W. Ray. Ray's Funeral Home and Florist, "The Home of Dependable Service 24 Hour Ambulance Service," telephone J-5901 residence R-4311; corner Fayetteville and Umstead streets, Durham N.C.
- 6. Jesus, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: T.R. Duncan Motor Co., "Bumper to Bumper Service--We repair any make of auto, welding, painting, radiator repairs and body work our specialty--Our Men Know Their Jobs," phone J-10951, 411 Poplar St. Durham N.C.
- 7. Jesus on a boat in a storm, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Daily devotions; Compliments of Smith's Fish Market, 718 Fayettevile St. Durham N.C., phone R-3491, L-7861 "We Deliver".
  718 Fayetteville Street was built around 1920 and originally occupied by Medliin's Seafood until the 1940s when it became Smith's Grocery which remained in the building until it was demolished around 1967. (http://www.opendurham.org/buildings/718-fayetteville)
- 8. Jesus praying, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Hayti Shoe Repair, phone R-4601; 713 Fayetteville St. Durham N.C.
- 9. Jesus with flock of sheep, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Holmes Cleaners, 530 E. Pettigrew St. Durham N.C., phone J-3892, J.R. Holmes prop., "We cater to dye work--Suits made to order."
  530 Pettigrew was part of one of the oldest commercial blocks in east Durham. It served as home to a number of businesses: Royal Tailoring (around 1930); a billiards parlor and Upchurch Temple (around 1941); Isler's Hotel (around 1950); Abraham Shaw Valet Shop (around 1954); Trixie's Pool Room (1959); Midway Sport Shop (1961); the block was demolished in the late 1960s. (https://www.opendurham.org/buildings/526-532-east-pettigrew)
- 10. Netherlands windmills, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Queen Pie Bakery, 432 W. Main St. Durham N.C., telephone J-0131, "Our specialty daily: Bread, Rolls, Pies, Cakes, Doughnuts, Etc. Let Us Make Your Birthday Cakes."
  Queen Pie Bakery was owned by Fendell Hodge (1900-1990).
- 11. Rural scene: house on water with ducks, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Holmes Cleaners and Dyers, "Suits Made to Order" phone J-3892, 530 E. Pettigrew St. Durham N.C., "The Home of Specialized Service."
- 12. Sermon on the Mount, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Sermon on the Mount; advertisements for Biltmore Esso Service Station, 402 East Pettigrew St. Durham, "We Specialize in Battery and Ignition Service" and Biltmore Cab, Theodore Speight manager, For Quick and Courteous Service, phone R-165.
  Theodore Speight ran a service station and repair center until forced to close and move during construction of the Durham Freeway in the 1960s. He eventually established Speight's Auto Service Center on Fayetteville Road in 1977, which is currently still in business. (https://durhamvoice.org/?p=31414)
- 13. Star of Bethlehem, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Speight's Auto Service, Hayti Auto Service, "A Business with a Soul" Theodore and Charlie Speight props., Wrecker Road Service, Pettigrew and Fayetteville St., Durham phone R-2571
  Theodore Speight ran a service station and repair center on Pettigrew Street until forced to close and move during construction of the Durham Freeway in the 1960s. He eventually established Speight's Auto Service Center on Fayetteville Road in 1977, which is currently still in business. (https://durhamvoice.org/?p=31414)
- 14. Vase with flowers, 1940s (Box 1)
  Back side: Jones Florist, "For the Best in Select Flowers Stop in and See Ours" phone F-4504, 704 Fayetteville St., Durham N.C.
  704 Fayetteville Street housed a number of businesses during the 20th century: Durham Mutual Life Insurance (1910s); Hayti Cafe (around 1923); Papa Jack's Rainbow Grill (around 1941; Papa Jack's at some point before the 1950s moved next door to 706); and Vanity Fair Beauty Salon (around 1954). (http://www.opendurham.org/buildings/704-fayetteville)
- 15. Vase with flowers, 1940s (Box 1)
- 16. Women's Army Corps, approximately 1942-1946 (Box 1)
  Back side: How to use the Bible when you need help; advertisement for T.R. Duncan Garage, 411 Poplar St. Durham, phone J-0951